（早希）《いい？　公生》
Listen to me, Kousei.
《繰り返し　繰り返し
楽譜を読み込んで→
I want you to study the sheet music over and over.
何度も何度も　弾き込むのよ》
Play it again and again.
《そうやって　完璧にするの》
That's how you're going to perfect it.
《譜面の指示どおり
作曲家の意図どおり》→
Just what the score calls for.
Just as the composer intended.
《完璧に　正確に》→
Perfectly and precisely.
You're off again!
《また　ずれた！
何度　言ったら　分かるの！》→
How many times do I have to tell you?
《そこが弾けるまで　寝ちゃ駄目よ。よく見なさい！》→
You're not going to bed until you can play that passage!
Pay attention!
《全ては　譜面に書いてあるのよ》
Everything is in the sheet music.
（男性）《また　有馬がトップか》→
Arima's No. 1 again?
Well, his mother is a direct disciple of Dr. Hashimoto.
《母親が
橋本先生　直系だからな》
I bet there's sheet music plastered onto those glasses!
（男の子）《眼鏡に　譜面でも
付いてんじゃね？》
Plus they'll hide the bruises after she hits him.
（男の子）《たたかれた
あざ隠しにも　なるしな》
He practices for seven or eight hours every day, right?
（女性）《７～８時間
レッスンなんでしょ？　毎日》
（女の子）《いつ　遊んでるの？》
When does he get any free time?
Most people couldn't stand that kind of life.
（女性）《そんな生活
普通　耐えられないわよ》
（女の子）《本当に　機械みたい》
He really is just like a machine.
（公生）
《みんな　勝手なことばかり》→
They don't know what they're talking about.
I'm the only one on Mom's side.
《僕が　たった一人
母さんの味方なんだ》
Let's go!
（かをり）いっけ～っ！
But will you be okay?
（椿）でも　大丈夫！？
練習は？　合わせたの？
What about practice? Have you rehearsed together?
No worries, we'll figure it out!
（かをり）平気　平気。
何とかなるって！
私たち　最強だもん。
'Cause we rule!
（渡）体育会系　なめんなよ！
合わせる時間くらい　つくれるぜ。
Don't underestimate us jocks!
If you need time to prep, you've got it!
（公生）ていうか　お前ら　学校は！？
この自転車　誰の！？
Wait, shouldn't you guys be in school?
And whose bike is this?
Hey, don't sweat the small stuff!
（渡）つまんねえ心配するなって！
うお～！
ぎりぎりセーフ！
Just barely, but...
Safe!
ギャ～！
（椿）公生！
Kousei!
Twitch
到着！　間に合った！
（渡）やるぞ！
Twitch
We're here!
We made it!
Let's do this!
Grab
二人とも　ありがとう。
いってくるね！
Drag Drag Drag Drag Drag
Thank you both!
Off we go!
Drag Drag Drag Drag Drag
（渡）こ…　公生　その靴。
スニーカーは　まずいぞ。→
Kousei, your shoes! Sneakers aren't gonna cut it!
俺の　履いてけ。
まだ　ましだろ。
Hurry! Hurry!
Put mine on! Better than what you've got, at least!
椿。　渡。　ありがとう。
Tsubaki, Watari...
Thank you. I've gotta go now.
いってくる。
早く　行け。　バカ。
Get out of here, moron.
C'mon, we're cutting it close! Step on it!
ほれ。　ぎりぎり　走れ～。
もっと　ゆっくり。
Slow down a little...
Hurry!
（椿）急げ！
ちゃんと　やれんのかなぁ
公生のやつ。
You think Kousei can pull this off?
（椿）もうすぐ　春が来るよ。
Spring will be here soon.
（渡）ん？　もうすぐ　５月。
桜が　散るころだぜ。
Huh?
It's almost May. The cherry blossoms are already gonna scatter soon.
（椿）うん。　でも　きっと…。
Yeah. But I just know...
（椿）春が　来るよ。
spring will come.
Towa Music Competition Committee Sponsor
Second Annual Towa Music Competition
Middle School Division Violin Section
（スタッフ）次　１２番の梨田さん　準備を。
Next: No. 12, Ms. Nashida. Please get ready.
（先生）よしっ。
目指すは　１位　通過よ。
All right! Your goal is to come out on top!
（梨田）は…　はい！
Y-Yes, ma'am! I'm gonna try to go out on top...
Man, talk about putting the pressure on...
（スタッフ）あ～あ
プレッシャー　かかっちゃって。
I-I'll do my best!
《こんなの　むちゃくちゃだよ》
This is beyond crazy.
《時間かけて　練習して
体に　覚え込ませて→
I should've put enough time into this to commit it to muscle memory,
譜面が　いらなくなるくらい→
fine-tuning it to the point that I don't need the sheet music.
完璧に　仕上げなきゃ
いけないのに》
《ほぼ　初見で
人に合わせなきゃいけないなんて》
But I'll practically be sight-reading when we play this together.
《しかも　あんな…》
If that weren't enough, she's such an...
《あんな　むちゃくちゃな
バイオリニストに》
Such an insanely out-of-control violinist!
準備完了。
All set!
テンポ　どうする？
がんがん　いっちゃう？
What tempo should we play at? Should we just go all out?
《無茶だ。　無謀だ》
This is crazy. It's reckless!
《こんな状態で
まともに　演奏できるわけない》
There's no way I can turn in a decent performance.
このドレス　似合う？　新調したの。
Don't I look good in this dress?
It's brand new!
《潔く　辞退した方が
傷は　浅くて　済む》
If I just put my foot down and back out of this now, it won't sting as much.
《こんなんじゃ　恥かくだけだ》
We're only gonna humiliate ourselves by going out like this.
無視…。
Ignoring me?
What?!
So did that calm you down?
どうかね。　落ち着いた？
What the hell is wrong with y—
いきなり　何するんだよ？
私を見て。
Look at me.
顔を上げて　私を見て。
Look up, and look at me.
下ばかり　向いてるから→
You're always looking down.
五線譜のおりに
閉じ込められちゃうんだ。
That's why you're caged inside those music scores.
大丈夫。
君なら　できるよ。
It'll be okay.
I know you can do it.
ずっと　昼休み　聴いてたでしょ。
You were listening to it every lunch break, right?
The sheet music was always somewhere in sight, right?
譜面は　いつも
目に入るところに　あったでしょ。
私たちなら　できる。
I know we can do it.
モーツァルトが
空から言ってるよ。
Mozart's telling us from up in the sky...
"Go on a journey."
「旅に出ろ」って。
"A man away from home need feel no shame."
旅の恥は　かき捨て。
思いっ切り　恥かこうよ。
Let's go out there and shame ourselves like crazy!
Together.
２人で。
１４番の　宮園かをりさん。
準備　お願いします。
No. 14, Ms. Miyazono Kaori.
Please get ready to go on.
Let's go!
行こう。
（早希）《いい？　公生。
譜面の指示どおり》→
Are you listening, Kousei?
Play as it's written in the score.
《全ては　譜面に書いてあるのよ》
Everything is in the sheet music.
《天真らんまん。　奇想天外》
Naive...
Bizarre...
It's like I'm on a rollercoaster, being flung around and around.
《ジェットコースターみたいに
僕は　振り回されてばかり》
《この人　自身が
行き先の分からない　旅のよう》
It's like this girl herself is a journey without a destination.
You're freedom itself.
君は　自由　そのものだ。
違うよ。
No, I'm not.
Music is freedom.
音楽が　自由なんだよ。
《僕たちのための　静寂》
This silence belongs to us.
《ここにいる　全ての人が→
Every single person here is waiting for us to break it.
僕らが　音を鳴らすのを
待っている》
さあ　旅に出よう。
Come on.
Let's go on a journey.
サンサーンスが
私たちを待ってるよ。
Saint-Saëns is waiting for us.
（椿）来た。
（渡）俺の　かをりちゃん。
Here they are!
My Kaori!
（観客）伴奏者も　子供だぞ。
Hey, the accompanist is a kid too.
（観客）あれ？
（観客）もしかして　あれって…。
Huh?
Wait, don't tell me that's...
（審査員）
《待ってました　宮園かをり》
I've been waiting for you, Miyazono Kaori.
《ん？　伴奏者が代わってる。
しかも　子供？》
She's got a different accompanist.
And he's a kid, no less?
何　やってんの？
椅子が　決まらないんだ。
What are you doing?
I can't set my chair just right!
早くしてよ　のろま。
両手　使って　調整。
Hurry it up, you slowpoke. Adjust it with both hands!
（審査員）《どっかで　見た顔だな》
He somehow looks familiar.
（観客）有馬だよ。　ピアノの。
（観客）有馬君？
It's Arima. You know, the pianist.
Arima?
Oh... So that kid is Arima Kousei, is he?
（風間）そうか。
あの子供　有馬　公生か。
That's right.
《そうだ。
成長してるが　あの顔は→
He's grown up since then,
but that's definitely the pianist, Arima.
ピアノの有馬。　有馬　公生》→
Arima Kousei!
So they know each other?
《知り合いだったのか。
というか　なぜ　伴奏を？》
Moreover, why is he playing her accompaniment?
ふぅ…　やっと　決まった。
もう…。
Finally got it right.
Jeez!
《ふ～ん　人工と天然》
Synthetic and organic.
《ずいぶんと
ミスマッチな　カップルだ》→
Talk about a mismatched couple.
《どんな演奏するつもりだ？》
What kind of performance do you have up your sleeves?
ハァ…　ふぅ…。
エロイムエッサイム　エロイムエッサイム
われは求め　訴えたり。
Elohim, Essaim. Elohim, Essaim.
Please give me your blessing.
顔が　こわばってるよ。
Your face is totally stiff.
《天才バイオリニスト
サラサーテに　捧げられた曲》
A piece dedicated to the virtuoso violinist, Sarasate.
《サンサーンス。
『序奏とロンド・カプリチオーソ』》
Saint-Saëns's Introduction and Rondo Capriccioso.
《よしっ。　うまく入れた》
All right, that was a good start.
《音も聞こえる。
この曲で　よかった》
I can hear the notes, too.
I'm glad we're doing this piece.
《ずれそうになる箇所も　あるけどバイオリンを　よく聴いて→
There are some parts where I could veer off key,
but if I listen closely to the violin and focus on the sheet music...
譜面さえ　確認していけば
技術的に　難しい曲じゃない》
Technically, it's not a tough piece.
《あぁ　公生が　また
ピアノを弾いてる》
Kousei's playing the piano again...
Miyazono Kaori.
《宮園かをり。　前回とは
打って変わって　おとなしいな》→
In a complete departure from her previous performance, she's being docile here.
《有馬に　気を使っているのか？》
Out of consideration for Arima, maybe?
《本性　出してきたな》
Now she's showing her true colors!
すげえ。
Awesome...
《音符が　消えてゆく》
The notes...
They're vanishing!
《ピアノの音が　聞こえない！》
The sound of the piano...
I can't hear it!
《ん？　どうした？》
Huh? What's going on?
（観客）あれ？　伴奏が…。
Huh? The accompanist...
《音が　バラバラ》
The sound is all over the place.
公生…。
Kousei...
《一音も漏らさず　驚くほど正確に弾けていた　伴奏者が→
The accompanist who played with such stunning precision, never producing a false note...
乱れてきた》
is starting to unravel.
《暗い海の底にいるように
何も聞こえない》
It's like I'm at the bottom of a dark sea where sound can't reach me.
《誰も　いない。
暗い　暗い　暗い…》
I'm all alone.
Enveloped in darkness.
So dark.
《僕は　暗い海の底で
独りぼっちになる》
I'm at the bottom of a dark sea...
and I'm going to be all alone.
（観客）《音　ガンガン出してるけどこんな伴奏じゃないよね》
He's pounding away at the keys, but this isn't how the accompaniment goes, is it?
（観客）《伴奏　最悪》
（観客）《バイオリン　好きだったのに》
This accompanist blows.
It's too bad. I liked the violin.
Despite being out of practice,
you were holding your own until now.
《不慣れながらも
バランスを取っていたのに》
《急に　どうした？　有馬》→
What's gotten into you all of a sudden, Arima?
《ピアノが　この演奏を
ぶち壊している》
The piano is destroying this performance.
《くそっ！　くそっ　くそっ！》
Dammit, dammit, dammit!
《こんなに　たたいてるのに
何でだよ？》
I'm hitting the keys so hard...
So why?!
《何で　僕のピアノの音だけ
聞こえないんだ！》
Why is it that the only thing I can't hear is my own playing?!
《賢明かもな》
Probably a smart move.
《減点は　免れないが
このまま　弾き続けたら→
A deduction's inevitable, but if he'd kept that up, it could've affected the violinist.
バイオリニストに
影響が　出かねん》
（観客）ピアノ　下手くそ。
（観客）邪魔すんなよ。
Lousy piano playing.
Don't mess it up for her!
（観客）最初から
弾かなきゃいいのに。
You shouldn't have been playing from the start.
《ごめん。
このまま　弾き続けたら…》
I'm sorry.
If I keep playing like this...
《僕が弾くと　君に迷惑が掛かる》
If I play, I'll only make this worse for you.
No way!
（観客）嘘でしょ？　バイオリンまで演奏　やめちゃった。
Now even the violinist has stopped playing!
Your Lie in April
ふぅ…　ハァ…。
これって　失格？
（観客）失格じゃないけど…。
Does this mean they're disqualified?
Well, not disqualified, but...
前代未聞だ。
This is unheard of!
終わったな。
That's all she wrote.
（観客）何で　やめちゃうんだ？
Why'd she stop?
There's no reason for her to
accommodate that awful accompanist.
（観客）下手な伴奏に
付き合うことないのに。
And she was so cool!
（観客）カッコ良かったのに。
《大丈夫。　私たちなら　できる》
It'll be okay.
I know we can do it.
《私の伴奏者に任命します》
I hereby appoint you as my accompanist.
《弾かなきゃ　駄目なの》
You still have to play.
《でも　君がいいの》
But I want you.
I'm gonna play with everything I've got.
《私は　全力で　弾く》
That way, the people who listen will never forget me.
《聴いてくれた人が
私を忘れないように》
《私は　演奏家だもの》
I'm a musician, after all.
アゲイン。
Again.
《この先は
暗い夜道だけかもしれない》
There might only be a dark path lying ahead of us.
《それでも　信じて　進むんだ》
But we'll push on all the same
《星が　その道を
少しでも　照らしてくれるのを》
and put our faith in the stars to light the way, if only just a little.
《さあ　旅に出よう》
Now...
Let's set out on a journey!
（観客）弾き直しって　ありなの？
Are they allowed to start over?
It's permissible as long as it's within the time limit,
（観客）時間内では
認められてるけど→
中断した時点で　無評価。→
but nothing after they stopped will count.
あの子のコンクールは
もう　終わったんだ。
This competition is over for that girl now.
（観客）じゃあ　あの子は
何のために　弾くの？
Then...
what exactly is she playing for?
何　やってんだ？　公生。
What are you doing, Kousei?
かをりちゃんを
一人で　弾かせる気かよ？
Are you gonna make Kaori play by herself?
Kousei...
（椿）《公生…》
《君のため…　君のため…》
For you...
《僕は　また
言い訳を探している》
I'm casting about for an excuse again.
I know we can do it.
《私たちなら　できる》
《君の目には　覚悟があった。
なら　その目に映った　僕には？》
There was resolve in your eyes.
So what was it that you saw in me?
《私が　いるじゃん。
顔を上げて　私を見て》
But you have me.
Look up, and look at me.
Look at me.
《私を見て》
《覚悟を決めろ！》
Brace yourself!
Now we're talking!
よっしゃ！
（椿）公生！
Kousei!
弾き始めた。
He started playing.
But their performances are still clashing.
《だが　まだ　音は　バラバラだ。
どうする？　有馬》
What'll you do, Arima?
《集中！　集中！　集中！》
Focus, focus...
Focus!
《音も　音符も
景気よく　消えてくれている》
The sound and the written notation are both disappearing.
《この一週間　いつも　譜面は
目に入るところにあった》
All week long, the sheet music was everywhere I looked.
I listened to it during every lunch break.
《ずっと　昼休みに　聴いていた》
《僕の中にあるものを
引っ張り出せ！》
I need to draw out what's inside me!
《集中！　集中！　集中！　集中！》
Focus, focus, focus...
Focus!
（早希）《いい？　公生》→
Are you listening, Kousei?
You mustn't play so violently.
《そんなに　乱暴に
弾いちゃ　駄目よ》→
《ピアノは　あなたなの》→
The piano is you.
If you touch it gently, it will smile.
《優しく　触れれば
笑ってくれる》→
《強く　たたけば　怒りだす》→
If you pound it with force, it will become enraged.
《赤ちゃんの頭を
なでるように》→
Touch it like you're caressing a baby's head.
All right, again.
《さあ　もう一度》→
Twinkle, twinkle, little star...
《♪♪「きらきら　ひかる
おそらの　ほしよ」》→
How I wonder what you are.
Up above the world so high...
《♪♪「まばたきしては
みんなを　みてる」》→
Like a diamond in the sky.
Twinkle, twinkle, little star...
《♪♪「きらきら　ひかる
おそらの　ほしよ」》
How I wonder what you are.
《音が　聞こえないなら→
If you can't hear the sound,
イメージしろ！
体中で　鳴らせ！》
then imagine it!
Play it with your whole body!
Draw out what Mom left you!
《母さんが　僕に残したものを
引っ張り出せ！》
《こらこら　友人Ａ》
Easy there, Friend A...
《主役を
食おうとするんじゃないわよ！》
Don't you dare try to steal my thunder!
《マジかよ…》
Are you kidding me?
キャ～　公生　かをちゃん　すごい！（観客）しーっ　しーっ。
Wow! Kousei, Kao, you're amazing!
奇麗だ。
She's beautiful.
Well, this is bizarre. They're both out of control.
《とんでもないな。
両者　めちゃくちゃ》
《まるで　殴り合いだ》→
It's like a brawl!
《その殴り合いに
会場が　のみ込まれていく》
And it's got the audience absolutely entranced.
《慣れてないのも　当然だ》
Of course he's not used to this.
《彼は　伴奏者じゃない。
彼女と同じ　ソリストだ》
He's not an accompanist.
He's a soloist, just like her.
《僕を突き動かす
力強く　鼓動のように》
She moves me.
Powerfully, like a heartbeat.
《君の音が　聞こえる》
I can hear your sound.
You're here.
《君が　いる！》
《もうすぐ　４月が終わる》
April will be ending soon.
（観客）ブラボー！
（観客）いいぞ！　中学生コンビ！
Bravo!
You middle-schoolers make a great duo!
（観客）最高！
（観客）アンコール！
That was awesome!
Encore!
厳粛な　コンクールで！
During a serious competition!
《乾いた　冷房。
ほこりの　におい》
The dry air-conditioning,
the scent of dust.
《僕は　旅に出る》
I...
I'm going on a journey.
Episode 4
Setting Out
Episode 5
Cloudy Skies
itsumademo soba ni itai to omoeta
I realized I never want to leave your side